A Frenchman walks into a restaurant in Egypt. He doesn t know what he wants to eat. Can
I see a menu? he asks. The Egyptian waiter says, Yes, menu. But he just stands there.
The Frenchman asks, A menu, please? The waiter says, Yes, yes, we have menu. Finally, the
Frenchman stands up and leaves while the waiter tries to understand what happened. What happened
was a false friend. False friends are words that sound the same but mean different things
in different languages. In this case, in French, a menu is a list of food offered at a restaurant.
In Arabic, menu means food. So the Frenchman wanted a list while the poor waiter just wanted
to make him understand that he was in a restaurant. False friends can be very dangerous for language
students. In Spanish, actual means happening currently, not real as it does in English.
To ask in Spanish if something is actually happening means, is it happening now rather
than is it really happening? That s a big difference, especially if you re talking about
a dangerous event. Bra is a funny one. In English, a bra is a kind of underwear. But
in Swedish, it means a good song. Imagine the looks you d get if you walked into a department
store in Sweden and asked for a bra. Demand is another example. In Italian, demand simply
means request. In English, it is more like a command, much more forceful. Imagine walking
into a cafe in the United States and saying, I demand a cup of coffee. You might get hot
coffee spilled all over your lap. False friends aren t really your friend. Be very careful
of words that sound just like words in your language. They may not mean what you think
they do.